Guide to the Mid-Atlantic early manuscripts collection 1974.002
Brooklyn Historical Society
Mid-Atlantic early manuscripts collection
1648-1867
Brooklyn Historical Society
Dering, Sylvester
1974.002
1.88 Linear Feet in one half manuscript box and one oversize box.
This collection contains correspondence, deeds, indentures, wills, land conveyances, genealogies, and printed materials from the 17th through 19th centuries. The majority of the collection relates to New York and the surrounding states, but some items are from New England or the Mid-Atlantic region. Materials are in English, French, and Dutch. Subjects of note include Native American relations and slavery.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Portions of this collection were the gift of Sylvester Dering, 1890. The source and date of acquisition for the remaining items in the collection are unknown. This collection was likely assembled by BHS staff from multiple donations at an unknown date. The collection was formally accessioned in 1974.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, deeds, indentures, wills, land conveyance documents, and printed materials authored by or pertaining to various figures from colonial and early national Long Island, New England, District of Columbia, Tennessee, and Europe. Many documents originate from prominent individuals, such as Lyman Beecher, King George III, John Paul Jones, Robert R. Livingston, William Penn, John Ross, Benjamin Rush, and Noah Webster. Items relate to early colonial and American conflicts, the Louisiana Purchase, slavery, and Native American affairs, particularly those involving the Cherokee Nation. Also included is a letter from General Toussaint Louverture, accompanied by a portrait image.
Some items are original, some are thought to be copies, and some are related to autograph-collecting.
Indians of North America; Slavery; Legal documents; Deeds; Correspondence; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Wills; Tennessee; London (England); Paris (France); United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; New Jersey; Pennsylvania; District of Columbia; South Carolina; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); Connecticut; Massachusetts; Virginia; United States -- History -- 1783-1865; New York (State); Louisiana Purchase; United States -- Politics and government; Genealogy; Debt; Mattituck (N.Y.) -- New York (State); Elections -- New York (State); Census; Bills of exchange; Articles of apprenticeship; Shipping records; Jamaica (New York, N.Y.); Dutchess County (N.Y.); Oyster Bay (N.Y.); Sermons; Suffolk County (N.Y.); Lake Champlain, Battle of, N.Y., 1814; Dering, Sylvester
- Gerritsen family genealogy, 1636-1766 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This folder contains a Gerritsen family genealogy (in Dutch), with entries dated from 1636 to 1766, various authors, three attached sheets.
  Gerritsen family
- Connecticut legal documents, Native American relations, and correspondence, 1648-1859; Gray, Ebenezer; Weekwakupp; Nomeonneeg; Neesantequaygus; Pynchon, John; Bradley, Increase; Huntington, Samuel, 1731-1796; Burritt, Elihu, 1810-1879 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  This folder includes nine documents with various authors from the Colony or State of Connecticut:
  - 1742 legal writ, addressed to the Sherriff of Windham County, CT, his deputy, or the Constables of the Town of Pomfret, re: a judgement obtained by William Brewster of Canterbury against Ezekiel Spicer of Pomfret, printed matter, signed by Ebenezer Gray, clerk, at Windham, with notes signed by William Brewster on the reverse.
  - March 21, 1648 original deed, with wax seals and signatures, transferring ownership of Mattituck on Long Island from the Sachem of the Corchaug tribal nation, Uxsquepassun[?], and his three brothers, Weekwakupp, Nomeonneeg, and Neesantequaygus to Governor Theophilus Eaton of the New Haven Colony and Steven Goodyear, Deputy Governor.
  - 1673 original contract binding Uncass, Sachem of the Munheags, living in Pamechaug [now,Montville, CT] to the Rev. James Fitch, minister of Norwich, CT, promising to deliver his people "in a constant way and solemn manner" to attend the holy services of preaching and prayer conducted by the Rev. Fitch. The document bears the mark of Uncass and the autograph signatures of witnesses John Tapscott, Thomas Stanton, and Samuel Mason.
  - August 1675 letter from Major John Pynchon at [Springfield?] to the "Honorable Governor & Magistrates ... in Connecticut Colony at Windsor or Hartford," re: news of fighting between Native Americans and English at Quabang [also known as Quaboag, now, Brookfield, MA] during King Philip's War. Pynchon requests for the sending of protective forces, mentions Judah Trumble.
  - August 1675 letter from Major John Pynchon, at [Springfield?], to "ye Honorable John Winthrop Esq. Governor of Connecticut in Hartford," re: intelligence he received from a Native American man, Nabaquassick, about "King Philip" and requesting additional forces be sent to "destroy" him.
  - 1729 land deed, with seal, between Nathaniel Finch and Justus Bush, both of Greenwich, CT, mentions Daniel Smith, witnessed by Caleb [?], Charles Tracy, and Gershom Lockwood.
  - 1780 Fairfield County, CT, summons from Increase Bradley, justice of the peace, to the Sherriff, re: Stephen Sturgis, defendant, to answer to Gideon Gray, plaintiff, regarding a dispute over unpaid debts. This document is printed matter with later notes on the reverse by various authors.
  - 1791 letter from Governor Samuel Huntington of Connecticut, at Norwich, CT, to George Clinton, Governor of New York, re: apprehension of persons wanted for the murder of Cornelius Hogeboom, late Sheriff of Columbia County, NY.
  - 1859 thank you letter from Elihu Burritt at New Britain, CT to "A. Ward Esq.," mentions Mr. Wadsworth.
  Brewster, William; Spicer, Ezekiel; Corchaug; Uncass, Sachem of the Munheags; Fitch, James, 1622-1702; Nabaquassick; Finch, Nathaniel; Bush, Justus; Sturgis, Stephen; Gray, Gideon; Hogeboom, Cornelius
- Document regarding Montauk ownership of Shelter Island, 1666 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This folder contains a 1666 legal document transcribing the words of Chegono on May 19, 1666 confirming that Catawamock (also known as Shelter Island) had been Montaukett land held by Montaukett Sachem Wyandanch's father. The document was witnessed by Nathaniel Sylvester, Robert Bond, and Isaac Arnold [men of Southold, LI, NY]. This document was also signed by John Mulford on July 22, 1666.
  Wyandanch, Sachem, circa 1620-1659; Chegono
- Massachusetts correspondence and donation receipts, 1669-1867; Ratlife, John; Hutchinson, Thomas, 1711-1780; Quincy, Josiah, 1710-1784; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  This folder contains five documents:
  - 1669 letter, from John Ratlife at Boston to the Commissioners at Hartford, re: the printing of Bibles.
  - 1771 letter from Governor Thomas Hutchinson at Boston to Sir Wiliam Johnson, re: "Proceedings of the Commissioners."
  - Three receipts acknowledging donations of materials to the public library from the Corporation of Harvard University at Cambridge. The receipts, printed matter, have autographs of three presidents of the university: Josiah Quincy (1843), Jared Sparks (1852), and Edward Everett (1867). The latter two receipts bear seals and a printed cut-out portrait of Everett affixed to the last (re: a donation by Henry Onderdonk Jr.).
- Long Island wills, 1673-1861; Wright, Anthony (Box 1, Folder 5, Box OS-38, Folder 2)
  This folder contains three items:
  - 1673 will of Anthony Wright of Oyster Bay. The will gives the bulk of his estate to his sister Alice Crabb.
  - 1685 will of Alice Crabb of Oyster Bay.
  - 1861 will of Ann Williams of Easthampton, names James Madison Huntting as executor, and mentions erecting a tombstone in memory of her grandfather Nathaniel Huntting.
  Crabb, Alice; Williams, Ann; Huntting, Nathaniel
- Deed of land, William Penn to George Fox, 1681 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  This folder contains a 1681 deed of land in Pennsylvania from William Penn at Worminghurst, Sussex to George Fox, of London, signed and sealed, witnessed by Herbert Springett, et al., with 1767 seal of recording at Philadelphia by Thomas Lusk.
  Penn, William; Fox, George
- Jamaica, LI, land deeds, 1713, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  This folder contains two items:
  - 1713 land deed, at Jamaica, Queens County, from Nehemiah Gail to Nicolas Haight, signed and sealed.
  - 1786 land deed, at Jamaica, Queens County, "Between R. M. [Taylor] administratrix of E. M. [Taylor] Late of Goshen Precinct in the County of Orange Taylor Decd. and Joseph Robinson of Jamaica in Queens County Esquire by the Honorable Thomas Tredwell Esq. Judge of Probates of the State of New York," unsigned, probably a copy.
  Gail, Nehemiah; Haight, Nicholas
- New York census acts and correspondence, 1713-1807; Milborne, Jacob (Box 1, Folder 8)
  This folder contains four documents:
  - 1713 letter [in Dutch] from Jacob [Milborne] at Rosendale [Ulster Co., NY], to [Cousin?] Ruth Bleeker at Albany. The letter mentions Bayard and Schermerhorn.
  - 1715 letter signed with three sets of initials and by a surrogate for [Pieter] Schuyler at Albany addressed "Gentleman," inscribed as a copy belonging to [Peter] Fauconnier and [Ebenezer] Wilson, re: division and settlement of Westenhook [Patent].
  - 1801 "Act for taking a Census in this State", printed matter, from the Office of Daniel Hale, Secretary of the State of New York.
  - 1807 "Act For taking a Census in this State" [New York], printed matter, unattributed, with manuscript notes on reverse indicating the number of electors enumerated in Flushing, Queens.
- Correspondence concerning relations between the U.S. government and the Cherokee Nation, 1718-1822; Johnson, Robert, 1677-1735; Graham, George, 1772-1830; Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1740-1823 (Box 1, Folder 9, Box OS-38, Folder 3)
  This folder contains four items:
  - 1718 letter from Governor Robert Johnson of South Carolina, addressed to "Mr. Speaker [sic] & Gentlemen," re: the necessity of sending a delegate to the Cherokees after reports of Cherokees being killed.
  - 1817 letter (Merriwether copy) from George Graham (1772-1830) Secretary of War, to General Andrew Jackson, Tennessee Governor Joseph McMinn, and General David Merriwether, regarding "the treaty entered into with the Cherokees" prior to its ratification by Congress.
  - 1822 letter from Return J. Meigs, at "Cherokee Agency" (70 miles from Knoxville, TN), to General John Floyd in Georgia, regarding preparations for a convention with the Cherokee, includes observations on the Cherokee and on the historical context of impending discussions.
  - 1835 letter from Cherokee Principal Chief John Ross (1790-1866), at Red Clay, Cherokee Nation [Tennessee], "to the Committee & Council in General Council convened," regarding recent transactions of correspondence between the Cherokee and branches of the US government, the failure of the latter "to respond to the grievances of the former, and a recounting of recent transgressions against the Cherokee.
- David Abeel correspondence, 1721-1730; Abeel, David (Box 1, Folder 10, Box OS-38, Folder 5)
  This files contains two items:
  - 1721 letter (in Dutch) from David Abeel, at New York, to his parents.
  - 1730 letter (in Dutch) from David Abeel, at New York, to his father, mentions "Capt. Ten Eyck."
- Correspondence of Adolph Philipse and Philip Hicks, 1728, 1770; Philipse, Adolph (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1728 letter from [Adolph] Philipse at New York to Rutger Bleecker, Evert Wendell, Ryer Gerrits, and Golon Van Schaick in Albany, regarding "Acts for Recovering of the Fines & Forfeitures", signed.
  - 1770 letter from Philip Hicks, at New York to his sister [address not given], regarding personal matters, mentions Uncle Bowne, "melancholy" times for business at New York, etc.
- Letter from William Pepperell, 1722; Pepperell, William (Box 1, Folder 12)
  This folder contains a 1722 letter from Sir William Pepperrell at Piscataqua to Captain Richard Sanderson, re: sloop and cargo, refers to Samuel Walker.
- Letter from Dr. Philip Doddridge, 1743; Doddridge, Philip (Box 1, Folder 13)
  This folder contains a 1743 letter from the minister Dr. Philip Doddridge, at Northampton, England, addressed to a gentleman ("My Honoured & very Dear Friend"), a warm and lengthy letter, mentions ministry at Gloucester, and the writing of hymns by Doddridge.
- Letter from Jacobus Bleecker to his parents, 1745; Bleecker, Jacobus (Box 1, Folder 14)
  This folder contains a 1745 letter from Jacobus Bleecker at New Rochelle to his parents at Albany (addressed to "Rutger Bleecker") [in Dutch], mentions his son "Johannis."
- Dutchess County colonial bills of sale and deeds, 1751-1766 (Box 1, Folder 15, Box OS-38, Folder 4)
  - 1751 land deed made between Silas Devel of Crom Elbow Precinct and Nicholas Trewer of Rhinebeck for 70 acres in "Lower Nine Partners"
  - 1756 inventory of Benjamin Pilcher of Crom Elbow Precinct
  - 1763 bond between Jacob Haight of Charlotte Precinct and Frederick Stryt of Rhinebeck.
  - undated bond of sale of "a negro man or slave called & named Jesson," purchased from James Gormond of Crom Elbow Precinct by Daniel Tobias. On the reverse is a 1766 bond of sale, conveying Jesson from Daniel Tobias to John Wilkinson of Beekmans Precinct.
  Devel, Silas; Trewer, Nicholas; Pilcher, Benjamin; Haight, Jacob; Stryt, Frederick; Jesson; Gormond, James; Tobias, Daniel; Wilkinson, John
- Bill for carpentry work from Thomas and Henry Dering, 1761 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  This folder contains a 1761 bill for carpentry work from Thomas & Henry Dering to Samuel Ruggles, also mentions Peirpoint and Ethridge [possible connection to the Dering (and Sylvester) family of Shelter Island, LI].
  Dering, Thomas; Dering, Henry; Ruggles, Samuel
- Bond of debt owed by Christopher Rodgers, 1765 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  This folder contains a 1765 bond of debt owed by Christopher Rodgers, schoolmaster of Stafford [County], VA, to Alexander Wodrow and John Neilson, printed matter.
  Wodrow, Alexander; Rodgers, Christopher; Neilson, John
- New Jersey official correspondence and letters of indenture, 1769-1830; Franklin, William, 1731-1813; Thompson, Charles, 1729-1824 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1769 letter from Governor William Franklin of New Jersey at Burlington to Sir William Johnson, re: Repeal of the American Duty Acts
  - 1784 formal letter from Charles Thompson, Secretary of Congress at Trenton to Governor George Clinton of New York, re: New York State delegates appointed to Congress
  - 1824 indenture, binding a seven-year-old boy, Jacob Teets, to farmer John T. Thayer of Independence, NJ, as apprentice, signed and witnessed.
  - 1830 indenture, binding a seven-year-old girl, Sarah Van Syckel, to William Vliet Sr. of Independence, NJ, as apprentice, signed and witnessed, with amendments dating to 1835, on reverse.
  Thayer, John T.; Teets, Jacob; Van Syckel, Sarah; Vliet, William, Sr.
- Suffolk County, LI, election records, resolution of the Continental Congress, and order for a census, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  This folder contains 5 documents recording Provincial Congressional business in Suffolk County townships:
  - 1776 record of elections in Huntington, Brookhaven, Southold, and Smithtown.
  - 1776 record of elections in Easthampton. Burnet Miller and Thomas Wickham Esquires were nominated and Miller was elected to serve as Candidate to represent the Town of Easthampton in Provincial Congress in New York.
  - 1776 record of elections at Shelter Island. Thomas Dering, Daniel Brown, Nicoll Havens, and James Havens were nominated for election.
  - Undated note, sworn to by "A. B." of Shelter Island, re: a resolution of the Continental Congress recommending the arrest of persons deemed dangerous to the Colony "or the Liberties of America."
  - Undated order for census, with recommendations for elections "to establish a new form of Government in this Colony."
  Miller, Burnet; Wickham, Thomas; Dering, Thomas; Brown, Daniel; Havens, Nicoll; Havens, James
- Revolutionary War correspondence, poetry, and military documents, 1779-1782; Bondinof, Charles; Brown, Benjamin; Jones, John Paul; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829; Morris, Robert, 1734-1806 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  This folder contains seven documents from the period of the American Revolution with various authors:
  - A verse entitled "To The Freeholders of Boston," no date, unknown author.
  - 1779 wartime letter from Charles Bondinof, at "Baskinridge," addressed to Colonel Fleming, re: Colonel Fleming's application to Congress for monies advanced to Colonel [William] Palfrey.
  - 1779 wartime letter from Benjamin Brown, addressed to "My Lord," re: Brown's request to be recommended to Governor Livingston, in order to gain command of a company "as a Continental Scouter" in the [New Jersey] State Regiment under Colonel Fell.
  - 1782 wartime letter from an unknown commanding officer to Colonel Willett and Colonel Reid re: orders to counter "the Enemy's approach" from Oswego, NY.
  - 1780 wartime letter from John Paul Jones at Nantes to a "M. De Genet," re: the ships Ariel and Alliance and supplies of clothing bound for America, refers to a Mr. Ross of Philadelphia.
  - 1782 wartime letter from Thomas [Timothy?] Pickering, at New Windsor to John Fisher at Fish Kill Landing, re: expected delivery of food stores from Fredericksburgh.
  - 1783 letter of exchange, with treasury seal, from Robert Morris, at Philadelphia to Nathaniel Appleton, Loan Officer of the State of Massachusetts, re: sets of Bills of Exchange drawn on Benjamin Franklin at the Court of Versailles to be delivered to Michael Hillegas, Treasurer of the United States.
  Palfrey, William
- Records of the Port of New York, 1788; Port of New York Authority (Box OS-38, Folder 1)
  This folder contactins a 1788 record of shipping entries and sorties, by nation, to/from the Port of New York [in French].
- Warrant from King George III, 1792; George, King of Great Britain, III (Box 1, Folder 21)
  This folder contains a 1792 warrant from King George III at the Court of St. James, London, to Dudley Ryder and Thomas Steele, Joint Paymasters General of H.M. Guards, Garrisons, & Land Forces, re: payment due to Lieutenant General James Johnston for the establishment of H.M. 2nd Corps Royal North British Regiment of Dragoons ["The Royal Scots Greys"].
  Johnston, James
- Letter from Dr. Benjamin Rush to Dr. John Cowan, 1795; Rush, Benjamin (Box 1, Folder 22)
  This folder contains a 1795 letter from Benjamin Rush, at Philadelphia, to Dr. John Cowan, at New York, re: the death of "your friend Mr. Grey", and inquiring, physician to physician, as to Dr. Cowan's remedies and practices.
  Cowan, John
- Documents relating to the Estate of John Parke Custis, 1795-1797 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  This folder contains three documents relating to the estate of John Parke Custis, step-son of George Washington:
  - 1795 estate division notice, including lists of enslaved people a part of the estate.
  - 1796 inventory, re: appraisal and division of the estate, including price breakdown of enslaved people a part of the estate.
  - 1797 legal decree, a copy signed by "P. Wagoner," re: a complaint between the heirs of this estate.
  Custis, John Parke, 1754-1781
- Toussaint Louverture documents, 1801; Toussaint Louverture, 1743-1803 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Undated [image published 1802] engraving, print, portrait of Toussaint Louverture ("General en Chef a St. Domingue").
  - 1801 thank you letter [in French] from Toussaint Louverture, at Port-Republicain (Port-au-Prince, Haiti) to Joseph Phillip Letombe, "Charge d'affaires et Commissaire general des relations Commerciales," at Philadelphia.
  Toussaint Louverture, 1743-1803
- Robert R. Livingston correspondence, 1801-1803; Livingston, Robert R., 1746-1813 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 180l letter from Robert R. Livingston (1746-1813), at Clermont, NY to his brother [Edward?] re: various subjects, including "ratification of the treaty," a mortgage, a Mr. Ludlow, and his brother's work.
  - 1803 letter from Robert R. Livingston at Paris to his brother re: negotiations for the Louisiana purchase, mentions James Monroe and Talleyrand, partly in cipher handwriting.
- Invitation from Thomas Jefferson to General John Armstrong, 1804 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  This folder contains a 1804 invitation, unsigned, author unknown, extended to General [John] Armstrong (1758-1843) from Thomas Jefferson, re: joining Jefferson and Mr. Madison for "family soupe" and to discuss the government's disposition towards the governments of Europe.
  Jefferson, Thomas; Armstrong, John, 1758-1843
- Lyman Beecher correspondence and Church documents, 1805-1839; Beecher, Lyman (Box 1, Folder 27)
  This folder contains six items:
  - 1805 letter from Lyman Beecher at Easthampton to Jonathan Huntting at Fishkill.
  - 1806 letter from Lyman Beecher at Easthampton to Jonathan Huntting at Southold.
  - 1811 letter from Lyman Beecher at Litchfield to Jonathan Huntting at Southold.
  - undated letter from Lyman Beecher at Riverhead to Jonathan Huntting at Southold.
  - 1824 copy of a sermon "To the Church of Christ in Huntington" sent by a committee of Jonathan Robinson, Lathrop Thomson, Peter H. Shaw, and Benjamin Norton at Southold, regarding a vote to separate from the Long Island Presbytery.
  - 1839 minutes of a meeting of the Long Island Presbytery at Sag Harbor.
- Account of the Battle of Lake Champlain, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  This folder contains a 1814 wartime letter from an unknown author, at Plattsburgh, to "Dear Sir" [address not given], with an inscription on the reverse by a different, unknown hand: "Description of the Battle of Lake Champlain by an officer whose name I have forgotten."
- Correspondence of General Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, 1818; Pinckney, Charles Cotesworth (Box 1, Folder 29)
  This folder contains a 1818 letter from General Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, at Charleston, SC, to Messrs. Williamson & De Villers, at Savannah, GA, re: a delivery to Dr. Aason [sic] of Liberty County, GA.
- Noah Webster autograph page, circa 1820; Webster, Noah (Box 1, Folder 30)
  This folder contains an undated page of dictionary by Noah Webster ("Aerography"-"Aerostation").
- Memorandum of S. Hambleton and correspondence of Henry G. Morton, 1820-1854; Morton, Henry G. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1820 memorandum notes, by S. Hambleton, "purser of the Columbus," at Washington, DC, regarding the fatal duel between Commodore James Baron and Commodore Stephen Decatur
  - 1854 letter from Henry [sic] G. Morton at Washington, DC, to "Dear Friend" [sic], regarding the sale of cattle. The letter mentions "McHenry of Baltimore."
  Baron, James; Decatur, Stephen, 1779-1820
- Ann Williams correspondence regarding debts, 1859-1861 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  This folder contains four letters to Ann Williams [of Easthampton?], re: debts owed to her: 1859, 1860, and 1861 letters from W. B. Williams at Allegan and Kalamazoo, Michigan, to his mother, and a 1861 letter from Mrs. C. Southworth, at Oneida Castle, New York.
  Williams, Ann
- Thank you letter from George Bancroft, 1885; Bancroft, George (Box 1, Folder 33)
  This folder contains a 1885 thank you letter from George Bancroft at Newport, RI to Abiel Abbot Low of Brooklyn.